

# Muhammad Haseeb Tariq

Data Scientist



mhaseebtariq@gmail.com



[Request on LinkedIn]



**Q** Utrecht, The Netherlands



https://mhaseebtarig.com



https://github.com/mhaseebtariq



https://nl.linkedin.com/in/muhammad-haseeb-tariq-3b817260



# **A**BOUT

I believe I have the ideal mix of skills when it comes to the applied and practical sides of data science. With over 12 years of professional experience I have been a part of many successful data initiatives (and projects), but more importantly I have also had my fair share of failures. Those failures have helped me greatly in becoming a strategic thinker. I attribute the success of my career to the following two aspects:

- 1. Consciously striving to surround myself with people who are smarter than me
- 2. Getting things done despite the most unfavorable circumstances

I am currently building models for TMNL...to catch the bad guys;)



# **WORK EXPERIENCE**

## Senior Data Scientist, Transaction Monitoring Netherlands (TMNL)

May 2021 - Present

TMNL is a joint initiative of five Dutch banks: ABN AMRO, ING, Rabobank, Triodos Bank and de Volksbank. With TMNL, these banks collectively monitor their payment transactions to look for signals that could indicate money laundering or the financing of terrorism. Some of my major responsibilities and projects include:

- Follow the money
- Anomalous transactions detection

#### Lead Data Scientist, BrandLoyalty

BrandLoyalty designs, develops and implements loyalty solutions that help the world's most successful retailers to change consumers' behaviour. Some of my major responsibilities and projects included:

- Exploring and prioritizing use cases
- Leading the data science adoption efforts and setting the strategic vision
- Hiring, training, and mentoring team members
- Program impact analysis using timeseries modeling
- RAVEN [Ratios and Volume Excellence]: A unique (demand forecasting) model implementation, combining the concepts of (both) Boosting and Bagging
- [Early phase] A predictive model for pre-empting redemptions

# Senior Data Scientist, Coolblue

Feb 2016 - Feb 2019 **③** 3 years

Coolblue is one of the largest online shops in the Benelux region. Some of my major responsibilities and projects included:

• GFM [Generalised Forecasting Machine]: A fully automated timeseries modeling engine for operational forecasting

- A recommender system that predicts the ideal sequence of pages, given the most recent (page) clicks of a user
- Google Adwords bidding schedule optimiser
- Early phase models: Pricing optimisation, email pressure, and fraud detection
- Training and mentoring the junior team members
- Assisting the hiring manager in the recruitment process

### Data Scientist, Convo

Convo is a work collaboration platform that goes beyond chat/messenger solutions. My major responsibilities and projects included:

- Utilizing data science to improve the overall user retention rate
- Exploratory analyses for understanding user behaviour and trends
- Implemented a customer churn model for improving the user onboarding wizard

## Data Analyst / BI Engineer, Pring

Dec 2008 - May 2014 **O** 5 years 6 months

Pring was one of the biggest micro-blogging services from Pakistan. Some of my major responsibilities and projects included:

- Developed an NLP model for extracting and matching (pre-selected) topics
- Extensively developed monitoring and reporting tools for Pring
- Lead and managed the side-projects for company's internship program
- During the earlier period of Pring, I also gained extensive experience in software/data engineering
  - ... [omitting those projects because of irrelevancy]



SKILLS

Programming: Python, R, Tensorflow, R Shiny, Django, Flask, JavaScript, D3.js, OOP, RESTful API Design

Databases: MySQL, MSSQL, PostgreSQL, Oracle, MongoDB, Cassandra, Redis

Cloud / Distributed Computing: AWS, GCP, Azure, Spark, Hadoop

MLOps: Unix-like operating systems, Docker, TeamCity, Apache Airflow



**EDUCATION** 

MSc in Advanced Computer Science (Data Science), University of Manchester, UK

2013 - 2014

BSc (Hons) in Computer Science, NCBA&E Lahore, Pakistan

2004 - 2008



INTERESTS

**Sports** 

Squash

Cricket

Cooking



Languages